New York State Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO, Environmental Conservation Division (PEF/ENCON); Records apap114
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO, Environmental Conservation Division 169 (PEF/ENCON) Records
1975-2000
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap114
23.17 cubic ft.
The Public Employees Federation (PEF) was founded in 1979 to represent members of the Professional, Scientific, and Technical (PS&T) bargaining unit of New York State. PS&T employees had formerly been represented by CSEA, the state's largest public employee union. PEF founders believed that the concerns of the PS&T unit were not adequately represented by CSEA, the majority of whose members were non-professional state employees. PEF's stated mission is to "provide the leadership necessary for PEF members to achieve employment security, higher wages, better working conditions, and improved retirement benefits." Materials in this collection document PEF activities at both the state and division level. There is extensive coverage of executive board activities from 1978 through mid-2000, annual conventions, committee meetings, and contract negotiations. Also included are files for PEF Division 169, PEF's Environmental Conservation Division. These include correspondence, agendas and minutes for labor/management meetings, material on committees, and administrative files. This collection also documents the activities of reform groups and political parties within PEF (most notably, the Statewide Coalition for a Democratic Union) and PEF's relationships with its national affiliates, the Service Employees International Union and the American Federation of Teachers. Particularly strong is the collection of bulletin board postings, which includes almost everything posted on Division 169 PEF bulletin boards from 1979 through 2000. There are also official PEF publications, including a near-complete run of PEF's official monthly newsletter to members, The Communicator.
Administrative History
The Public Employees Federation (PEF) was certified in 1979 as the collective bargaining agent for the members of the Professional, Scientific, and Technical (PS&T) unit of New York State. This unit includes scientists, doctors, nurses, engineers, teachers, social workers, counselors, and a wide variety of other professionals employed throughout New York. ["This Is PEF", Series 6, Box 1, Folder 17]. PS&T employees had formerly been represented by CSEA, the state's largest public employee union. PEF founders believed that the concerns of the PS&T unit were not adequately represented by CSEA, the majority of whose members were non-professional state employees. After these employees voted in April 1978 to be represented by PEF rather than CSEA, CSEA launched a legal attack against PEF to stop the loss of some 45,000 members to the new union. The legal battle continued through early 1979; CSEA charged PEF organizers with forging thousands of signatures on ballots in the PS&T vote on PEF representation. These charges were eventually deemed to be unfounded by the New York State Court of Appeals in March 1979, and PEF was legally certified as the collective bargaining agent for PS&T employees. [ "PEF - 1978 to 1988", The Communicator, Convention Supplement, October 1988, Series 6, Oversize Box 2, Folder 4].
PEF began negotiating its first contract with the state on April 23, 1979. The contract was accepted by members in December 1979, against the recommendation of the Executive Board. ["PEF - 1978 to 1988", The Communicator, Convention Supplement, October 1988, Series 6, Oversize Box 2, Folder 4]. Contracts were originally negotiated for a three-year period; in 1991, a four-year contract was negotiated for the first time. [1991-1995 Professional, Scientific, and Technical Unit Contract, Series 1, Box 2, Folder 25]. In many cases, negotiations with the state on a given contract were so prolonged that the previous contract expired before a new one took effect. This usually led to controversy regarding "sunset" benefits, provisions of the expired contract which the State refused to honor when a new contract had not been agreed upon.
One contract issue of primary concern to PEF in the years documented by this collection was the state retirement system. In the 1970s New York State implemented a tiered retirement system, in which workers' retirement benefits varied considerably based on their original date of hire. PEF has long lobbied for the abolishment of the tier system, but has not been successful. Other issues of long-term concern for PEF include maintaining a high level of health care coverage for its members, preventing the outsourcing of state jobs to private contractors, preventing layoffs in the face of state budget cuts, insuring timely and fair performance evaluations, and guaranteeing parking privileges for members working in downtown Albany.
Political controversy within the union was common in its early years. PEF's first president, John Kraemer, was investigated on charges of being a "no-show" employee at his previous position with the New York State Department of Labor. [Personnel Abuses at the Department of Labor", State of New York Commission of Investigation, July 1979, Series 1, Box 4, Folder 49]. After being voted out of office in 1982, Kraemer was convicted of embezzling funds from the union. ["Unionist's Career a Stormy One", Albany Times Union, 6 March 1987, Series 1, Box 4, Folder 49]. Kraemer's successor, Elizabeth Hoke, caused controversy by revoking the union leave of PEF's three statewide vice presidents. ["Unions Open Query Into PEF Dispute", Albany Times Union, 24 May 1984, Series 4, Box 3, Folder 38]. Later, she was charged with using her PEF credit card for personal expenses. ["Hoke 'Censors' Union Article on Credit Card Use", Albany Times Union,11 September 1984, Series 4, Box 3, Folder 38]. The Statewide Coalition for a Democratic Union (SCDU), a group dedicated to reforming PEF, had originally backed Hoke's election bid; by 1985, they had renounced their support of her and actively supported opponent Rand Condell's presidential campaign.
As of 1999, PEF represented approximately 55,000 workers throughout New York State. Five full-time officers are elected by union members: a president, three vice-presidents, and a secretary-treasurer. Three elected trustees serve as independent monitors of PEF's finances. Members also elect 1000 delegates to an annual convention where major policy decisions are made. A 120-member executive board handles policy decisions between conventions. At the local level, members elect officers and shop stewards in about 230 local divisions, each of which represents PEF workers in a specific building or facility. PEF is also divided into 12 geographical regions, each with a regional office and member-elected coordinator. ["This Is PEF", Series 6, Box 1, Folder 17].
PEF divisions are the equivalent of what most other unions call locals. Divisions, usually based around a given state agency or workplace, began to form in May 1981. ["PEF - 1978 to 1988", The Communicator, Convention Supplement, October 1988, Series 6, Oversize Box 2, Folder 4]. Division 169 consists of PEF members employed by the Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC) throughout New York State, excluding Long Island. Division 169 is also referred to as PEF/ENCON.
PEF's stated mission is to "provide the leadership necessary for PEF members to achieve employment security, higher wages, better working conditions, and improved retirement benefits". ["Mission", http://www.pef.org/, 25 June 2004]. PEF is affiliated with New York State United Teachers, the American Federation of Teachers and the Service Employees International Union. ["This Is PEF", Series 6, Box 1, Folder 17].
During the years covered by this collection, PEF presidents were John Kraemer (1979-1982), Elizabeth Hoke (1982-1985), Rand Condell (1985-1991), Howard Schafer (1991-1994), James Sheedy (1994-1997), and Roger Benson (1997- ).
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection document PEF activities at both the state and division level. Contract negotiations were a central activity of the union and are well-documented. Other statewide activities include PEF's annual convention, held throughout New York in locations that included Niagara Falls, Syracuse, and Buffalo. There is extensive coverage of executive board meetings from the board's inception in 1978 through mid-2000; meeting kits for each meeting contain agendas, minutes, memos and correspondence, news clippings on issues relevant to board discussions, and a wealth of other materials. The executive board held regular meetings on a quarterly basis; special meetings were held at PEF's annual convention or when extenuating circumstances warranted additional meetings, such as when the Executive Board needed to vote on whether to send a proposed contract to PEF members for final approval. There is also documentation of statewide lobbying and campaigning activity through the Political Action Committee, as well as documentation of other state and local committee activities. There is some documentation of both state and local Women's Program meetings and events.
This collection also documents PEF's relationship with its affiliate unions, the American Federation of Teachers, New York State United Teachers, and the Service Employees International Union. In 1983, PEF president Elizabeth Hoke took legal action to sever PEF's affiliate relationships, arguing that the affiliation agreements were exploitative. The New York State Supreme Court ruled against PEF, and the affiliate relationships were maintained. The collection contains extensive coverage of the affiliation dispute case. There are also files on conventions held by PEF's affiliates.
Also included are many files for PEF Division 169, PEF's Environmental Conservation Division (frequently referred to as PEF/ENCON). These include correspondence between the Division and PEF headquarters, agendas and minutes for labor/management meetings, committee files, and administrative files. Particularly strong is the collection of bulletin board postings, which includes almost everything posted from 1979 to 2000 on Division 169 PEF bulletin boards. New York State was contractually required to provide these bulletin boards to PEF for communication with members.
This collection also documents the activities of reform groups and political parties within PEF - most notably, the Statewide Coalition for a Democratic Union (SCDU), which was active in the presidential campaigns of both Elizabeth Hoke (1982) and Rand Condell (1985, 1988).
The collection is particularly strong in official PEF publications. Included is a near-complete run of PEF's official monthly newsletter to members, The Communicator, dating from 1979-1990 and 1994-1999. Other publications include Steward News, Shop Talk, contract update newsletters, retirees' newsletters, and several regional and divisional newsletters.
This collection does not provide much documentation of division activities outside of Division 169, nor of regional activities beyond region 8, which encompasses the Capital District. The collection also lacks material related to rank-and-file members and the effect of the union on their lives. It contains no membership rosters for either the state or division level.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are arranged both alphabetically and chronologically; see series descriptions for more specific detail. Generally, material within folders is in chronological order, with undated materials at the end of the folder.
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1978-2000
Series 2: Labor/Management Files, 1981-2000
Series 3: Executive Board, 1978-2000
Series 4: Committees, Programs, and Events, 1975-2000
Series 5: Division 169 Bulletin Board Postings, 1979-2000
Series 6: Publications, 1978-1999
Series 7: News Clippings, 1979-1999
Series 8: Memorabilia, 1984-1985, 1988, 1999, undated
Acquisition Information
Records in this collection were kept by Stanley Byer, who was involved in PEF at the state and division level since its inception. From 1978 through 2001, Byer served in a variety of roles in the union, including executive board member, trustee, shop steward, and division secretary. Byer also participated in numerous PEF committees and events, including statewide election campaigns and annual conventions.
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Stanley Byer of New York State Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO, Environmental Conservation Division 169 in April 2001 and April 2003. Additional material was transferred by Susan J. DuBois in October 2006.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives include: Civil Service Employees Association (CSEA), Local 1000, AFSCME (APAP-015); United University Professions (UUP) (APAP-039); William Kelsey (APAP-152); Solidarity Committee of the Capital District (APAP-042); and Albany Central Federation of Labor (APAP-143). Additional labor collections can be found at the Department's Labor subject page.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Labor; Albany, New York; Civil service--New York (State); Government employee unions--New York (State); Labor laws and legislation--New York (State); Labor unions--New York (State); Agendas; Budgets; Clippings; Constitutions; Contracts; Correspondence; Minutes; Newsletters; Reports; Benson, Roger; Byer, Stanley; Condell, Rand; Hoke, Elizabeth; Kraemer, John; Kraemer, John; New York State Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO--Environmental Conservation Division; American Federation of Teachers; Civil Service Employees Association (N.Y.); Service Employees International Union; Statewide Coalition for a Democratic Union
- Administrative Files, 1978-2000; 1; 7.2 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes administrative files for both statewide PEF operations and Division 169. Where necessary, files related to statewide PEF are marked as "New York State PEF" to prevent confusion. Division 169-specific files are marked as "Division 169". There are numerous subject files. The collection's creator did not distinguish between subject and administrative files. This series includes files related to contracts and contract negotiations, PEF's relationships with its affiliates, PEF history, constitutions and by-laws, elections, retirement plans, health insurance and other benefits, PEF policy, steward training, and many other aspects of PEF and Division 169 operations. There are a number of designated correspondence files; however, correspondence is also found throughout this series and others in subject files.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1983-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Affiliate Convention Delegate Elections, 1980; 1986; 1988; 1992; 1994-1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Affiliation Agreement, PEF - SEIU - AFT/NYSUT, 1979; 1983; 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Affiliation Agreement Case, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Affiliation Agreement Case, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Affiliation Agreement Case, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Affiliation Agreement Case, 1987-1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Affirmative Action, 1981; 1983; 1985-1987; 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - "Affirmative Action in New York State", Hearing Report, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Agency Codes, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Agency Fee Refunds and Union Dues, 1984-1986; 1989; 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Agency Shop, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Aid to the Nicaraguan Contras, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Albany Central Federation of Labor, Constitution, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organization, 1979; 1985-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - American Federation of Teachers, 1984-1990; 1992-1994; 1996-1998; 2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - American Federation of Teachers, Constitution, 1988; 1990; 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - American Federation of Teachers, Report of the Officers, 1983-1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Arthur Young Report on Classification and Compensation, 1982; 1985; 1989; 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Arthur Young Task Force / Pay Equity, Impact of Pay Equity Implementation Report on the Professional, Scientific, and Technical Unit, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Attendance Rules, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Audit Standards of Government Organizations, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Auditors' Reports, 1982-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Badillo, Herman, Election Campaign, 1984; 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Benefit Information, 1978-1979; 1981; 1995; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Benson, Roger E., 1987; 1989-1990; 1993; 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Bloch, Edward, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Boycotts, 1986-1987; 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Budget, 1983; 1985; 1994; 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Business Council of New York State, 1991; 1992; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Byer, Stanley, Ethics Grievance Petitions, 1998; 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Byer, Stanley, Executive Board Candidacy, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Calendar, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Carnegie Forum on Education and the Economy, Report of the Task Force on Teaching as a Profession, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Child Care, Joint Custody, 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - Civil Service Employees Association, Agency Shop Fee, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - Civil Service Employees Association, Contract, 1982-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
  - Civil Service Employees Association, Contract, 1991-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
  - Civil Service Employees Association, EnCon Local 655, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
  - Civil Service Employees Association and Law Enforcement Employees Contract Agreements, 1991-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
  - Civil Service Employees Association, Reports, 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 47)
  - Civil Service Law, 1979; 1983-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
  - The Communicator, Correspondence, 1979; 1981; 1983-1985; 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 49)
  - Constituency List Review, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 50)
  - Contract Demands, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Contract Demands, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1982-1984 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1985-1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1992 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1994-2000 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Contract Negotiations, News Clippings, 1984-1985; 1987-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Contract Negotiations, News Clippings, 1990-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Contract Negotiations, Newspapers, 1985; 1988; 1992 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Contract Negotiations, Pamphlets, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Contract Negotiations, Payroll Lawsuits, 1992-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Contract Negotiations, PEF and State Proposals, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Contract Negotiations, Rally Memos and Photographs, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Contract Negotiations, State Proposals, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Contract Negotiations, Steward Postings, 1990-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Contract Settlement Summary, 1988-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Contract Surveys, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Contract, Tentative, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Contract, Tentative, 1995-1999 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Contracts, 1979-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Contracts, 1988-1999 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1984; 1988; 1992-1994 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 January-1995 February (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 March-1995 April (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 May (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 June (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 July (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 August (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 September (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 October (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1995 November-1995 December (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 January (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 February-1996 March (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 April-1996 June (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 July-1996 September (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 October (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1996 November-1996 December (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1997 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1982-1989 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)